did Bret contris truly invent the hip
thrust in this video I'm going to give
all of my naysayers all the evidence
they need to think that I'm a total
fraud I'm also going to provide all the
evidence to my proponents to indicate
that Breet contr is legit the real
deal all right first things first the
date is October 10th 2006 I'm in
Scottsdale Arizona where I bought my
first home I'm watching UFC fights it
was Ken Shamrock versus Tito Ortiz it's
their third fight I don't care who wins
I just didn't want one guy to dominate
the other I want it to be a good fight
and Tito Slaughters Ken he's on top he's
ground and pounding and in my head I'm
thinking why isn't Ken Shamrock trying
to escape the mount why isn't he bucking
his hips as a certified strength The
guishing Specialist I start thinking the
wheels start turning I'm going there
should be an exercise to strengthen that
motion and I'm going okay you need load
how would you load up you can't have a
dude straddle you you can't just be like
hey bro can you straddle me and I can
pump out like 50 reps so we need a way
to load it and ideally you wouldn't be
limited by the floor you could sink your
hips deep and move the hips through a
full range of motion so I went out to my
garage gym okay I put four 45lb plates
and looped them together with a dip belt
I figured that's 180 lb an average guy
probably weighs around 180 lb let's give
that a try I moved my glute ham
developer next to my reverse hyper I
stood inside of the dip belt and picked
the weights up and kind of
simultaneously leaned back onto the
rounded backpad of the glute ham
developer got the weight up onto my hips
and put my feet up on top of the reverse
hyper now looking back it was very
dangerous what if they would have slid
apart and I would have come crashing
down but luckily the unit stayed put I
sunk my hips down really deep thrusted
them upwards I got about 15 reps in and
I had to stop and at that point I had
never felt my glutes working that hard
to where I thought the muscle was going
to strain I stopped the set I walked out
into the front yard I'm not religious
I'm not even very spiritual I remember
it like it's yesterday this is over 18
years ago I looked up in the sky and I
said from this point forward my whole
life changes I'm going to do everything
in my power to make this exercise as
popular as humanly possible and I've
done exactly that I have not wavered
from that goal crazy how your life can
be going this way and then you think of
something and like that you turn on a
dime and now it's going this way and
that's what really catapulted me
eventually into being the glute guy and
having Booty by Brat and BC strength and
all of this kind of came from that idea
now my first hip thrust invention was
called the scorcher I quickly got to
work right after that UFC fight I'm
having my clients do it and I tell my
aunt who I was training at the time I
say you know I wish I could popularize
this exercise I think I'm going to write
a Teen Nation article I'm finally ready
to write my first Teen Nation article
tation stood for testosterone nation it
was a online magazine featuring the best
strength coaches in the industry that's
where all the good ideas from the late
'90s and early 2000s even up until the
mid 2010 all the best ideas came from
tnation.com but I said it sucks because
to do this exercise it requires a glute
ham developer a reverse hyper and it's
still dangerous like they could split
apart you could hurt yourself so I don't
think it'll get as popular as could
possibly be and she said well design
something design a piece of equipment I
said I don't know what I'm doing she
goes sure you are you were always a
great artist let's draw it so right then
and there I got out a pencil I drew it I
in fact I drew a bunch of drawings and I
wanted to protect them so I actually got
them notorized back in the day I drew up
all these designs for different hip
thrust apparatuses and I applied for a
patent and I actually have the patent
for hip thrust machines I have not been
enforcing it because I feel guilty
enforcing my own invention but yeah all
the manufacturers right now I could be
collecting from every one of them I'm
probably leaving $1 to $2 million on the
table from not enforcing my patent but I
wasn't all about the money I just wanted
this to be as popular as possible and I
wanted hip thrust to eventually be as
popular as like a lap pull down machine
and a leg press like if you go to a
commercial gym they should have a lap
pull down a leg press and a hip drust
and it's finally happening now the hip
drust units are actually the most
popular selling pieces in the industry
you go to the big trade shows the most
popular manufacturers right now are
booty Builder and glute Builder and the
world is finally getting the hip thrust
devices so I designed the Scorch and it
was initially for just band hip thrust
and single EG hip thrust in 2007 I had a
few units made and I gave one of them to
celebrity trainer Gunner Peterson he
calls me shortly afterwards he goes
Brett I'm training Jayla right now this
is her favorite exercise imagine me a
former high school math teacher turned
personal trainer open up my first gym
and hearing that and he goes but you
need handles you know they're wobbly
they're unstable put some handles on
that so I put handles on it now we're
doing single leg hip thrust with handles
we're doing band hip thrust but the
loaded dip belt didn't work out that
well so you know I was doing a dumbbell
then I was using two dumbbells like this
and then I realized what if you could
use a barbell well you need some thick
bar padding so I Google search thick bar
padding and voila Hampton was making
thick barbell pads and the Hampton was a
total Game Changer we also started using
ax balance pads but the Hampton was a
game changer from that point forward we
started using the barbell with the thick
bar pads doing barbell hipos off The
Scorch but it was tough because you need
two trainers to pick up the barbell the
lifter would slide down underneath and
you would thrust against resistance we
also did barbell plus band which to this
day is the highest EMG activity I've
ever recorded in the gluteus maximus was
this variation here I am sporting a
mohawk so we only did scorcher hip
thrust in 2006 to 2008 but then the
economy collapsed the housing market
collapsed companies were going bankrupt
gyms were closing plazas were closing I
had attracted investors for scorcher
they backed out cuz they lost all their
money and land deals every business in
my Plaza went under and I'm left going
what do I do now so I've always been a
hard worker and I thought hm I should
start writing I'm going to start writing
for teenage I'm going to start up a Blog
start up YouTube I'm a start up social
media and that's exactly what I did but
now with scorcher being under I'm
thinking how can I popularize this it
wasn't until then around 2008 till I
actually thought of using a regular
bench and back then it didn't feel the
same cuz if you've always done shoulder
and feet elevated like the scorcher
doing it off the flat ground off of a
bench feels weird it doesn't feel quite
as effective but then I found whatever
you get used to that's what you like the
most anything else kind of feels weird I
realized in order to teach the world how
to hip thrust I've got to teach them
using basic equipment and so finally in
around 2008 the idea was born for the
barbell hip thrust now why did I come up
with the idea it was because the
strength coaches that came before me
were talking all about low-load glute
activation and we were doing glute GL
Bridges and they were recommended glute
Bridges I never did a glute Bridge my
entire life in my opinion that was for
like Jane Fonda and like tamily webs you
know Buns of Steel she was doing glute
Bridges with body weight but the
strength coaches that were popular
before me especially the ones riding for
teen like Eric cresy and Mike Robertson
they were telling powerlifters you know
get down and do your glute Bridges
before you do your squats and your
deadlifts and they're also saying you
know use a band and do x-band walks and
do these little drills and it'll wake up
your glutes and you'll perform better on
your compound movements so I I remember
doing a glute bridge I go wow these work
really well but the only problem is I
can do like a 100 I wish you know they
were harder cuz this feels really good
if it weren't for those coaches you know
Mark vertigan Mike Bole Eric cresy and
Mike Robertson Martin Rooney all these
legendary stength coaches at the time
were promoting low-load glute activation
in the dynamic General warm-up I don't
think I would have ever thought of the
hip thrust but I had never seen anyone
do a loaded hip thrust before we did
body weight glute Bridges one leg and
twole and we did feet elevated glute
Bridges one and two legs but no one ever
did shoulder elevated glute Bridges
before 2006 so I started doing barbell
hip thrust barbell glute Bridges and
single leg hip thrust and I invented all
three of them you're going to have a
hard time believing this like a single
leg hip thrust putting your arms across
a bench and doing single leg hip thrust
there's no evidence of anyone ever doing
those before 2006 and we were doing
those dual elevated as well and so what
I decided to do is I wrote an ebook in
2009 I launched this ebook it was called
Advanced Techniques and glui maximize
strengthening I started up a Blog I
started writing for Teena the article
was called dispelling the glute myth and
this was the article heard around the
world I came out of the block strong you
know I wanted to make a ripple and I
didn't just make a ripple I created a
tital wave within a couple weeks
everyone in the industry was talking
about hip thrust it's a brand new
exercise no one's ever seen it before
teenan had this really popular Forum I
have guys riding me from New Zealand
guys riding me from all over the world a
few years later when I went and got my
PhD in Auckland New Zealand I met the
guy he's like do you remember this I'm
the guy who wrote you I was doing 45lb
hip thrust the day after you published
that article now at that time no one
accused me of not inventing it that
would have been the time where people
said hey Brett this is awkward we've
been doing hip thrusts in Norway we've
been doing them in Brazil we've been
doing them in this location but no one
said that why because no one was doing
them like that would have been the time
for people to say look here I am doing
hip thrust so nobody ever accused me of
stealing them or not inventing them in
fact people started calling it the
contus hip thrust the CHT and I stopped
them I said you don't need to call it
the contus hip thrust I don't want it
named after me because our industry was
always a very crediting industry like
everyone knew that Dan John invented the
goblet squat we knew who popularized
what together the first is the Goblet
Squad I invented the Goblet Squad uh
there's no question about that I love it
when people take credit for it and
they've only been in the field for a
decade because I invented it uh right
around the turn of the millennium we
knew Pavo sauline made Kell swings
popular we knew that Paul chck made
stability puls popular we knew that JC
Santana made sled pushing more popular
we knew that Mike Bole made Single
legegg movements more popular and then
Ben Bruno made them even more popular we
were always so credit if you didn't give
credit you didn't go anywhere in our
industry and then the world took a huge
turn in the Tik Tok Instagram era where
no one credits anyone and because no one
credits anyone anymore no one knows the
history of things so now that it's like
18 years later when I post something
saying I invented the hip thrust I get
all these people saying lol this has
been around for hundreds of years and it
in fact has not so anytime someone says
that I said hey if you have evidence of
it existing please tell me please show
it to me I'd be happy to credit the
rightful inventor and I always get the
same response every single time without
fail they say LOL we didn't have camera
phones in the late '90s or the early
2000s blows my mind cuz these people are
so insanely stupid that they think that
there's no history before camera phone I
have this book super strength by Alan
Calvert written in 1924 it's 101 years
old and it has hundreds of images in
black and white of exercises being
performed by strong men we have history
of exercise going back over a 100 years
we have pictures from the early 1900s we
took our cameras to the gym people made
documentaries people made movies people
created videos we recorded our videos
before camera phones I started YouTube
in 2009 we didn't have camera phones at
that time we had regular cameras so if
hip thrust existed and were popular
there would be evidence of it you'd see
in the movie Pumping Iron you'd see
Arnold lifting and you'd see people in
the background doing hip thrust and when
I wrote my glute ebook I did my research
I spent a whole week now you might think
okay he's exaggerating no I spent seven
straight days searching for about 12
hours a day and I thought of every term
that you could possibly search like what
could you call this exercise the first
word could be supine floor glute pelvic
hip the second term could be Bridge
thrust raise pushup lift you get the
point I did every combination of those
and I'd search 30 pages deep on Google
I'd even go into the forums that were
popular back then and search 30 pages
into those and I was able to find like
some convict uh conditioning type
program where the guy was glute bridging
with a keg he had a keg in his lap but I
never saw anyone doing any like loaded
hip thrust or shoulder elevated s hip
thrust and so yeah I claimed the
exercise now at that time I had never
seen or heard of anyone doing a hip
thrust before me and I never saw any
evidence but since then there is some
evidence and so now I'm going to start
the second part of this video which is
going to give all the evidence to my
haters to say see here's from contas
himself saying that other people
invented the exercises but you can
decide for yourself so it's kind of
crazy if you look at the evolution of
the bench press and the evolution of the
hip thrust there are a lot of parallels
like bench pressing was scoffed at when
it became popular the arguments by
weightlifters at the time were like real
man lift weights standing up you you do
standing curls and shoulder presses and
clean and jerk squats and deadlifts you
don't lay down and lift weights they
called it a lazy man's exercise they
said you unnaturally develop your
pectorals instead of your delts which
were more functional you're doing this
unfunctional exercise and it's going to
give you poor posture and those are the
same arguments I've seen for the hip
thrust it's kind of funny how history
repeats itself self but anyway with the
bench press all right it was being done
in you know the late 1800s in fact
George hackin Schmidt set a record of
361 lb but they didn't have benches back
then and you didn't use spotters so you
had to lay down on the floor you had to
do kind of a pullover and press so you
had to just pull the bar over your head
and then press it so he did a 361 lb
pull over and press and that was like
1898 these records are kind of murky
because you get different dates and
different amounts according to different
sources but yeah it was like 1898 1899
361 or 32 pounds George hackin Schmid a
couple years later a got by the name of
George lurich he actually hit 443 lb but
he did it with a belly toss okay I'll
get to that in a minute so hackin Schmid
laid flat okay he his back stayed flat
on the ground a guy by the name of Joe
nordquest in 1917 he hit 388 lbs but he
would Bridge up because you realized
when you bridge it's like a decline
press and you're A Little Bit Stronger
so lifters started bridging up but
lifters were also at the time doing this
belly toss where they would fling the
weight they would do an explosive glute
bridge and catch the weight overhead
they also start making bigger discs like
bigger plates like 19in plates so you
just have to turn your head to the side
and you could roll it over you didn't
have to do the pullover portion and
sometime in the late 1920s I can't find
the exact date a guy by the name of Bill
Lily he just start getting stronger and
stronger with this ridiculous technique
he would just take the bar bridge Bridge
up Bridge up Bridge up and he would
extend his hips and spine all the way to
lock out and then just kind of move the
bar overhead and sit back down so he
didn't do any actual pressing he just
bridged the bar he had incredible
flexibility and he just bridged the bar
overhead at that time people started
thinking okay this is ridiculous Bob
Hoffman was an authority back then he
said let's Outlaw that let's ban that
let's make a standardized technique
where you have to lay your back flat
then benches started becoming popular
and in the early 19 1950s you had actual
bench presses appearing but you needed
spotters and then finally you had
stations with the support so you could
do it on your own then bodybuilder start
doing it then in the early 60s a group
got together in the UK started doing the
strength set which was how much can you
squat bench press and curl and then that
set the stage for powerlifting the curl
was replaced with the deadlift and now
the bench press is the most popular
exercise in the world it's used by
bodybuilders it's used by powerlifters
even the guys who like standing
exercises who would scoff at the bench
press they realized that the bench press
could help strengthen your military
press and lock out heavier weight and
they even start doing it you also see um
oldtime strong men doing neck Bridges
with weight they'd Bridge up onto their
necks but they were trying to strengthen
their necks you see them doing the tomb
of Hercules where they'd have like posan
and stuff in a bridge position but I
don't think that works your glutes that
much it's kind of like a whole body lift
but yeah the bench press techniques
weren't done with the purpose of working
your glutes they were done to bench
press more weight and it was was only
done for one rep so if you can't stand
me and you want to say I'm a fraud you
can look at these old school images and
be like people were bridging up with
weight many many years ago in the early
1900s you know well over a 100 years
before Brett contas came around I
discovered this in around 2009 when I
was researching for my ebook this here
is a picture out of the book super
training by Mel siif which was published
in 2003 but in this book it has a
picture from Yuri rosansky from 1977
check out these drawings how cool is
this these are hypos variations and they
were said to be a special exercise to
Aid in the development of sprinting for
track and field athletes and you had
simultaneous hip extension on one leg
and hip flexion on the other leg and
what's funny is now a a review paper was
just published last year in 2024 saying
that hip thrust and horizontal movements
are superior to Vertical hip extension
exercise and plos for developing
sprinting speed so this was like 50
years ahead of its time but anyway you
see kettle bells being used on the foot
you see a person pushing against the
hips these are indeed hip thrust
variations but it's not a barbell hip
thrust with your back on a bench and I
never saw these until after I invented
the hip thrust but yeah if you're a Bret
Ker's hater you can say that verosky
rest in peace he was an awesome Soviet
Sports scientist you can call him the
father of the hip thrust all right the
third piece of evidence I have is this
book that I got in 1995 my cousin bought
it for me I still have it it's called
The Complete Book of butt and leg
development a couple of Brothers wrote
it and you look through this book my
cousin Brian bought it for me for
Christmas because I was training him at
the time and I got this in '95 you know
I was 19 years old I was so enthralled I
actually took it I went into my room and
I read the whole book cover to cover in
the middle of my family Christmas party
and I said why did you get me this book
mind you this is 20 years ago he says
because I've never met someone so
obsessed with the glutes that was 20
years ago to this day I'm still so
obsessed with the glutes my enthusiasm
for the glutes has never waned never
dimin but in this book I looked through
it I read all the exercises they do
mention glute Bridges they're body
weight glute Bridges now I didn't see
this till years later just a couple
years ago I was looking through the book
and I have it at my coffee table at my
home in Las Vegas and I'm looking
through the program section at the end
and in the advanced programs it has
weighted pelvic Bridges or weighted
glute Bridges whatever they call it but
they don't have a picture of that but
how did they wait it did they want you
to put a plate there anyway you could
say they came up with the idea in 1995
but there were no images of it so we
have the history of the bench press with
the oldtime strong man doing explosive
Bridges catching the lockout we have
veros shon's drawings we've got the
Complete Book of button legs and finally
the fourth and most damning piece of
evidence is from Beyonce nolles this
clip I'm about to show you comes from
2003 this is from a VH1 series called
Rock bodies that they featured they did
on a bunch of you know female singers
and artists at the time and yeah this is
Beyonce from 2003 check this out look at
this footage she's doing barbell hip
thrust off of a stability ball and I
think this is her trainer here so does
anyone know the name of this woman if so
she could be thought of as the inventor
of the barbell hip thrust I didn't see
this until a few years ago someone sent
it to me and I just wrote it off cuz
I've been accused for so many years I
just wrote it off and I'm like I should
check what if what they're saying is
true I looked into it and I'm like oh
that doesn't come from this lady got the
idea from me this is is from probably
like 2012 or something no this is from
2003 this came 3 years before I invented
the barbell hip thrust so Beyonce
Beyonce's trainer congrats you can give
the credit to them if you want and say
they invented the barbar hip thrust but
it's not done off a bench there's no
padded bar and it's not done heavy so
whatever the case may be whoever
invented the hip thrust I will go down
in time as being the person who
popularized it because the heaviest we
went on the off the scorcher me and my
trainers would do 405 we do 45lb hip
thrust and then I remember I went to New
Zealand I came back I started training
people out of my garage I remember my
client Sammy was the first one to do a
45lb hip thrust then we just kept
rolling with that and then eventually
invented the hip Thruster and we started
having competitions my client Carly
eventually hit a 765 lb hip thrust with
a great lockout and we developed a whole
system for maximizing strength on the
hip thrust you're always going to be
limited by the lockout power so we would
do probably a third of our volume being
regular hip thrust and then 2/3 of our
volume being lockout work being pause
hip thrust bar plus band hip thrust or
hip thrust pulses or like one and a
quars where you do extra emphasis on the
lockout and at my first glute lab in San
Diego out of like 25 girls the average
thrust strength was 550 lbs at a body
weight of 140 so the average woman at my
gym was hip thrusting four times body
weight which is crazy they're doing 315
for 20 with ease 405 for 10 you know 495
for a few reps but yeah Queen Carly she
want hit 405 for 30 so then we had the
hip Thruster eventually came the hip
Thruster 3.0 with the rotisserie pad
with the rotary pad we call them rotiss
hip thrust now you have the Thruster Pro
and now you have Hammer strains you've
got booty Builder glute Builder you've
got Nautilus glute Drive you've got all
these different hip thrust devices out
there and I'm so happy that glute
training has evolved not just the hip
thrust and glute bridge and single leg
hip thrust all the hip thrust variations
but also the increased glute training
frequency and the acceptance of
horizontal and lateral glute exercise
because back in the day vertical was all
we did you know you did squats you did
lunges you did rdls and that's it now a
good glute training program is also
includes those exercises and it also
includes your hip thrust your back
extension your Kickback and then also
plenty of abduction movements to develop
that well-rounded 3D glute shape that is
so sought after in this day and age so
there you have it that's the history of
the hip thrust I hope you enjoyed the
history lesson thank you for watching my
video if you like the video please give
it a thumbs thumbs up let me know your
thoughts in the comment section and make
sure you're subscribed to my channel
because YouTube is going to be my number
one focus in 2025 thank you for watching
I'm Brett contur aka the glute guy